A Guide to the Lewis F. Powell Jr. Papers, 1929-1998
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, Washington and Lee University
- Personal Papers 1921-1996
  - Family Papers 1941-1998
    - Correspondence
      - Siblings
        - Zoe Powell Lane 1943-1995 (Box-folder 47/1-8)
          Correspondence with spouse Kenneth Lane is included here. Separate file concerning the 1995 death of Zoe Powell follows the general correspondence.
        - Eleanor Powell Dewey 1937-1996 & n.d. (Box-folder 47/9-30)
        - Frank L. Dewey (brother-in-law) 1936-1971 (Box-folder 48/1-2)
          This is the spouse of Eleanor Dewey.
      - Extended Family
        - Helen Doak (aunt), 1953-1995 (Box-folder 48/3-6)
        - Ken Lane (nephew) 1964, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 48/7)
        - Helen Elizabeth Powell (Niece), 1961, 1978-1994 (Box-folder 48/8)
        - Edward "Ned" Angus Powell Jr. (Nephew) 1966-1993 (Box-folder 48/10)
        - E. Bryson Powell (Nephew) 1968-1994 (Box-folder 48/9)
        - Katherine Powell Rolph (Niece) 1973-1992 (Box-folder 48/11)
        - Mary Lewis Dewey Grow (Niece) 1953-1995 (Box-folder 48/12)
        - Annie Neill McLean 1948, 1964, 1967 (Box-folder 48/14)
        - Cola A. Powell 1937, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 48/15)
        - Eleanor Gwathmey 1925 (Box-folder 48/16)
        - Ernest with Mary Lewis Gwathmey 1942, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 48/17)
    - Subject Files 1936-1988
      The Subject Files are dominated by correspondence and records concerning Bear Island, a plantation in Hanover County, Virginia that had been the childhood home of Powell's mother, Mary Lewis Gwathmey. Powell spent much time there as a child, as did his children, in their turn. Later it served as a family retreat and gathering place. Powell's painful--and later regretted--decision to sell this property is extensively documented here. Also present in this subseries are records of the Powells' 1969 African safari, including Josephine R. Powell's diary of the experience.
      - Bear Island 1936-1986
        - Correspondence
          - General 1947-1984 (Box-folder 49/1-19)
          - Farming Operations 1965-1968 (Box-folder 49/20-23)
        - Memoranda 1965-1966 (Box-folder 49/24)
        - Deeds 1920-1966 (Box-folder 49/21-28 & 50/1)
        - Subject Files (Box 14)
          - Engineer Report Photos 1958 (Box-folder 50/2)
          - Farming Expense Statements 1965-1966 (Box-folder 50/3)
          - Graveyard 1966, 1977-1980 (Box-folder 50/4)
          - Insurance 1965-1966 (Box-folder 50/5)
          - Sale 1966 (Box-folder 50/6)
          - Taxes 1958-1966 (Box-folder 50/7)
          - Title To Property 1966 (Box-folder 50/8)
          - Writings
            - The Sale of Bear Island and After the Sale of Bear Islandp. 1966 & p. 1977 (Box-folder 50/9)
            - Bear Island Memories 1984 (Box-folder 50/10)
            - A Few Anecdotes and Some of My Memories of the Bear Island Family n.d. (Box-folder 50/11)
      - Biography (Mary Lewis Dewey Grow) 1986-1988 (Box-folder 50/12-13)
      - Dancing, notes re n.d. (Box-folder 50/14)
      - David M. Lea & Company, Inc. 1948, 1952 & 1970 (Box-folder 50/15)
      - Fiftieth Wedding Anniversary 1986 (Box-folder 50/16)
      - Firearms 1968-1977 (Box-folder 50/17)
      - Picture for Apartment (Robert Goodnough) 1980 (Box-folder 50/18)
      - Teaching-University of Richmond 1938-39 (Box-folder 50/19-21)
      - Trips
        - European Trip 1957 (Box-folder 50/22-23)
        - Russia Trip 1958
          - Diary 1958 (Box-folder 51/1)
          - Report 1958 (Box-folder 51/2-3)
        - Mexico 1964 (Box-folder 51/4)
        - European Trip 1966 (Box-folder 51/5)
        - Safaris 1967-1972
          - Correspondence 1967-1972 (Box-folder 51/6-12)
          - Diary (Josephine R. Powell) July 1969 (Box-folder 51/13)
          - Itinerary & Visa 1969 (Box-folder 51/14)
          - Receipts 1969-1970 (Box-folder 51/15)
      - Wager On Roosevelt-Landon Election 1936 (Box-folder 51/16)
    - Financial and Legal Records 1929-1995 (Box 52-98)
      Note: Permission of the archivist is required before using these records.
      In addition to general records, the "Financial and Legal Papers" include files specifically about contributions, insurance, investments, real estate holdings, bank borrowing, tax returns, trusts and wills. As one would expect, the "Memos to Executors" that accompany Powell's wills contain information on such subjects as Powell's complex finances and his wife's separate estate. Also present, however, are letters to his wife expressing his hopes for his children's futures, detailed funeral and burial plans, and mention of some records management decisions he had made concerning his Supreme Court papers.
      The "Real Estate" records form the largest portion of this subseries. Real property holdings of Powell's wife and mother-in-law are treated here, as are properties he owned jointly with his wife. Properties he owned in his own right and through his development company, Huguenot Land Corporation, are also documented.
      The "Trusts" deal with legal instruments for both Powell's own family members, and the children of Powell's World War II friend, Lowell P. Weicker. Powell was the executor of the Weicker trusts.
      - General 1942-1995 (Box 52)
        - World War II 1942-1944 (Box-folder 52/1)
        - Expenses 1951 (Box-folder 52/2)
        - Option Agreement, David M. Lea and Company 1956 (Box-folder 52/3)
        - Family Financial Affairs 1952-1973 (Box-folder 52/4-20)
        - Arrangements with Hunton & Williams on Leaving the Firm 1972 (Box-folder 52/21-23)
        - Swiss Annuity 1972 (Box-folder 52/24)
        - Hollywood Cemetery Lot 1965-1984 (Box-folder 52/25-29)
        - Josephine Rucker Powell 1978-1995 (Box-folder 53/1-2)
        - 1238 Rothesay Road 1987-1992 (Box-folder 53/3-8)
      - Check Registers 1953-1995 (Box 54-60)
      - Contributions 1963-1994 (Box 61-64)
      - Financial Statements 1953-1983 (Box 64-65)
      - Insurance 1932-1992
        - General 1932-1992 (Box 65-68)
        - Accident 1957-1970 (Box-folder 68/19-20)
        - Automobile
          - General 1936-1959 (Box-folder 68/21)
          - re Accidents 1967-1968 & 1982 (Box-folder 68/22-27)
        - Cashing-in Policies 1972 (Box-folder 68/28-29)
        - Conversion to Paid-Up Policies 1970-1972 (Box-folder 68/30-32, Box-folder 69/1)
        - Health/Medical 1951-1986 (Box 69)
          - General 1951-1952 (Box-folder 69/2-3)
          - ABA 1955-1965 (Box 16A)
          - David M. Lea & Co. 1957-1971 (Box-folder 69/4)
          - Hunton & Williams 1938 (Box-folder 69/5)
          - New York Bar Association 1964 & 1967 (Box-folder 69/6)
          - Josephine R. Powell 1975-1986 (Box-folder 69/7-19)
        - Liability 1962-1968 (Box-folder 69/20-22)
        - Life
          - General 1961-1972 (Box-folder 69/23-27)
          - Colonial Williamsburg 1958-1971 (Box-folder 69/28)
          - David M. Lea & Co. 1943, 1954-1964 (Box-folder 69/29)
          - Hunton & Williams 1947-1962 (Box-folder 69/30, Box-folder 70/1-3)
          - Miller & Rhoads 1953-1963 (Box-folder 70/4)
          - Phi Delta Phi 1962-1972 (Box-folder 70/5)
          - Southern Railway 1965-1971 (Box-folder 70/6)
          - Virginia Bar Association 1960-1970 (Box-folder 70/7)
          - Virginia Manufacturers Association 1953-1968 (Box-folder 70/8)
          - Virginia State Bar 1952 & 1971 (Box-folder 70/9-10)
        - Southern Railway System 1960-1971 (Box-folder 70/11-13)
        - Survivor's Annuity 1976-1996 (Box-folder 70/15-18)
        - Wedding Gifts 1936 (Box-folder 70/19)
        - Marvin P. Rucker's Policies 1936-1954 (Box-folder 70/20-21)
      - Investments
        - Correspondence 1936-1990 (Box 71-74)
        - Josephine McRae Rucker 1952-1971 (Box-folder 74/11-16)
        - Josephine Rucker Powell 1971-1994 (Box-folder 74/17-34)
        - Custodian Accounts 1969-1971 (Box-folder 74/35-37)
        - Children 1942-1972 (Box-folder 75/1-8)
        - Chesterfield Land and Timber Corporation 1954-1987 (Box-folder 75/9-24)
        - Sperry and Hutchinson Company 1969-1972 (Box-folder 75/25-30)
      - Real Estate
        - Josephine McRae Rucker 1938-1961 (Box 76-80)
          - Indebtedness to American Bank & Trust 1938-1946 (Box-folder 76/1)
          - Gresham Estate 1952-1956 (Box-folder 76/2)
          - McRae Estate 1949-1961 (Box-folder 76/3-7)
        - Josephine Rucker Powell
          - 1238 Rothesay Road 1933-1987 (Box-folder 76/8-29, Box-folder 77/1-9)
          - Park City, Utah 1979-1982 (Box-folder 77/11-12)
          - Deer Valley, Utah 1979-1982 (Box-folder 77/13-16)
        - Lewis F. and Josephine R. Powell
          - Leases 1983-1943 (Box-folder 77/17-19)
          - Walters Tract, Chesterfield County 1941-1947 (Box-folder 77/20)
          - Stuart Avenue Property Sale 1945-1946 (Box-folder 77/21)
          - Atlantic Horizons Apartments 1967-1972 (Box-folder 77/22-26)
        - Lewis F. Powell, Jr.
          - Chesterfield Land Investments 1957-1964 (Box-folder 78/1-9)
          - Rothesay Tennis Association 1959-1960 (Box-folder 78/10)
          - Swift Creek Land Investments, Inc. 1968-1988 (Box-folder 78/11-24)
          - Huguenot Land Corporation 1969-1978 (Box-folder 79/1-28, Box-folder 80/1-7)
          - Purchase of Washington Apartment 1971 (Box-folder 80/1-8-9)
          - Brandermill Lot 1975-1978 (Box-folder 80/10-11)
      - Bank Borrowing 1957-1978 (Box-folder 80/12-19)
      - Taxes 1929-1994 (Box 81-92)
      - Trusts
        - Correspondence and Memoranda 1964-1971 (Box-folder 93/1)
        - Trusts established by Lewis F. & Josephine R. Powell 1957-1994 (Box 93, Box-folder 94/1-23)
        - Trusts Established by Others
          - Josephine McRae Rucker 1956 (Box-folder 94/24)
          - David M. Lea Stock Trust 1954-1977 (Box-folder 94/25-29)
          - Lowell P. Weicker Family Trusts 1950-1968 (Box-folder 94/30-32, Box-folder 95/1-11)
      - Wills
        - Wills of Family Members
          - Mary Lewis Gwathmey Powell 1941-1973 (Box-folder 96/1-12)
          - Louis F. Powell 1940-1984 (Box-folder 96/13-29)
          - Eleanor Powell Dewey 1954 (Box-folder 97/1)
          - Josephine Powell Smith 1959-1963 (Box-folder 97/2)
          - Ann Pendleton Powell (Carmody) 1960-1963 (Box-folder 97/3)
          - Josephine Rucker Powell 1964-1986 (Box-folder 97/4-6)
          - Josephine McRae Rucker 1973, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 97/7)
            Concerning the settlement of her estate.
          - Alice Watkins Powell 1974 (Box-folder 97/7A)
        - Wills of Lewis F. Powell Jr. 1943-1992 (Box-folder 97/8-20)
          - Power of Attorney 1958-1980 (Box-folder 97/17)
          - Memoranda 1958-1992 (Box-folder 9/18-20, Box-folder 98/1-7)
          - Correspondence 1969-1992 (Box-folder 98/8-25)
    - Medical Records 1948-1996 (Box 99-102)
      These records are closed to researchers.
  - Records re Education 1921-1932 (Box 103-110)
    Records re Education, (2 cu.ft.) consists primarily of notes taken in class and in preparation for class while Powell studied in the law schools of Washington and Lee University and Harvard University. The professors' names, when known, are included in the container list with the corresponding notes. Bar review notes and some exams are also present. Powell's undergraduate thesis is included with legal education materials, as he was already taking law classes in his late undergraduate days in order to finish both degrees in six years. There are also some writing assignments from his prep school days at McGuire School.
    - McGuire's University School
      - The Prep(yearbook) 1922 (Box-folder 103/1)
      - Report Card 1924 (Box-folder 103/2)
      - English Class Writings 1921-1922 (Box-folder 103/3)
      - Algebra Exam 1925 (Box-folder 103/4)
    - Washington and Lee University
      - Undergraduate Academic Papers
        - English 1925-1926 (Box-folder 103/5-9)
        - History 1926 (Box-folder 103/10)
        - Thesis: The Constitutionality of Minimum Wage Laws for Women1929 (Box-folder 103/11)
        - Report Card and Commencement Program 1931 (Box-folder 103/12)
      - Student Government 1925-1930
        - Correspondence 1928-1929 (Box-folder 103/13-14)
        - Executive Committee Financial Records 1930 & n.d. (Box-folder 103/15)
        - Miscellaneous Papers 1925 & n.d. (Box-folder 103/16)
        - National Student Federation 1930-1931
          - Correspondence 1930 (Box-folder 103/17-21)
          - Fifth & Sixth Annual Congresses 1930-1931 (Box-folder 103/28)
      - Address Book n.d. (Box-folder 103/29)
      - School of Law
        - Class Papers 1931
          - Swift v. Tyson Feb. 28, 1931 (Box-folder 103/30)
          - Three Jurisdictional Landmarks March 30, 1931 (Box-folder 103/31)
          - Recognition of Validity and Incidents of Marriages Between Whites and Blacks April 28, 1931 (Box-folder 103/32)
        - Class Notes 1929-1932
          - Property I c. 1929 (Box-folder 104/1)
            Taught by Clayton E. Williams
          - Property II c. 1930 (Box-folder 104/1)
          - Property III c. 1930 (Box-folder 104/1)
          - Wills c. 1930 (Box-folder 104/2)
          - Trusts c. 1930 (Box-folder 104/2)
            Taught by Clayton E. Williams (?)
          - c. 1930 (Box-folder 104/2)
          - Property IV c. 1930 (Box-folder 104/2)
          - c. 1930 (Box-folder 105/1)
            Taught by William H. Moreland
          - c. 1930 (Box-folder 105/1)
            Taught by Charles R. McDowell
          - c. 1930 (Box-folder 105/2)
            Taught by Raymon T. Johnson
          - c. 1930 (Box-folder 105/2)
          - c. 1930 (Box-folder 105/2)
          - c. 1930 (Box-folder 105/2-3)
          - c. 1930 (Box-folder 106/1-12)
            Taught by Charles P. Light, Jr. (?)
          - c. 1930 (Box-folder 106/13-15)
          - c. 1930 (Box-folder 106/16-21)
          - c. 1930 (Box-folder 106/22-28)
            Taught by William H. Moreland (?)
        - Bar Review Notes c. 1930-1931 (Box-folder 106/29-40, Box-folder 107/1-11)
      - Printed Materials 1929-1934 (Box-folder 107/12)
    - Harvard Law School 1931-1932
      - Class Papers 1932
        Written for Prof. Dodds' Seminar in Corporate Finance
        - Regulation of Public Utility Issues in Michigan Jan. 8, 1932 (Box-folder 108/1)
        - Smith v. Oldtown Sheet and Tube Company Mar. 2, 1932 (Box-folder 108/2)
        - Fairness of a Proposed Reorganization of General Gas and Electric Company April 18, 1932 (Box-folder 108/3)
        - Analysis of the Proposed Deed of Trust on the Property of the Interstate Electric Railway Company, a Virginia Corporation 1932 (Box-folder 108/4)
      - Class Notes 1931-1932
        - Equity III 1932 (Box-folder 108/5-16A)
          Includes exam. Taught by Prof. Chafee
        - Administrative Law (Box-folder 108/17-20)
          Taught by Felix Frankfurter.
        - Public Utilities (Box-folder 108/21-28)
        - Corporate Finance 1932 (Box-folder 109/1-17)
          Includes exam. Taught by Prof. Dodd
        - Jurisprudence 1932 (Box-folder 109/18-29, Box-folder 110/1-10)
          Includes exam. Taught by Roscoe Pound.
  - Speeches, Statements, and Writings 1937-1971
    Speeches, Statements, and Writings (7 cu.ft.), includes: lists of selected speeches; the speeches and writings themselves; and materials related to the speeches and writings. This last category includes: drafts; correspondence about travel and publication arrangements; and research materials.
    A frequent public speaker throughout his career, no one knows how many speeches Powell delivered. The speeches and writings in this subseries--and throughout these papers--should not be considered as the complete body of Powell's work. References are made throughout the papers to speeches not found here. Certain other portions of these papers contain speeches and informal talks which are not present in this series. (See also: Speeches, Interviews and Writings series in United States Supreme Court and Retirement subgroups for speeches made after 1971.)
    One folder containing lists of selected speeches precedes the speeches themselves. These lists represent at least three unpublished compilations of Powell speeches. One was made just before Powell became American Bar Association President-Elect. The second was done immediately following Powell's ABA Presidency. The last was assembled for his Supreme Court nomination hearings.
    - List of Selected Speeches c. 1946-1970 (Box-folder 111/1)
    - Speeches, Statements and Writings
      - The President's Proposal to Pack the Court, March 16, 1937 (Box-folder 111/2)
        Talk to the Omnibus Club, Richmond, Virginia,
      - Popular Misconceptions About the Supreme Court, May 8, 1938 (Box-folder 111/3)
        Richmond, Virginia (?)
      - Kiwanis Club, September 12, 1938 (Box-folder 111/4)
        Richmond, Virginia
      - Community Fund, 1938(?) (Box-folder 111/5)
      - Soldiers' and Sailors' Civil Relief Act of 1940, May 23, 1941 (Box-folder 111/6)
        Virginia State Bar Association, Charlottesville, Virginia.
      - Are We Prepared to Fight, June 11, 1941 (Box-folder 111/7)
        Omnibus Club, Richmond, Virginia
      - Oral Report to the Junior Bar Conference, September 28, 1941 (Box-folder 111/8)
        Indianapolis, Indiana
      - Bill of Rights, c. 1941 (Box-folder 111/9)
      - Judicial Review -- Its Proper Place in the American Plan of Government, c. 1941 (Box-folder 111/10)
        Alexandria Bar Association, Alexandria, Virginia
      - Speech on Behalf of Senator Byrd, July 15, 1946 (Box-folder 111/11)
        AMVETS at the Mosque, Richmond, Virginia
      - Speech on Behalf of Senator Byrd, July 31, 1946 (Box-folder 111/12)
        American Legion Post 200 at the John Marshall Hotel, Richmond, Virginia
      - "Why I am for Byrd", August 1, 1946 (Box-folder 111/13)
        WMBG radio station, Richmond, Virginia
      - National Association of Referees in Bankruptcy, August 22, 1946 (Box-folder 111/14)
        Welcome on behalf of the Bar Association of the City of Richmond.
      - Introduction of Air Marshall Sir William Elliot, c. 1946 (Box-folder 111/15)
      - Unveiling of the Portrait of Major Charles O. Saville, April 22, 1947 (Box-folder 111/16)
        Statement On Behalf of the Bar Association of the City of Richmond
      - Unveiling of the Portrait of Judge Frank T. Sutton, Jr., May 29, 1947 (Box-folder 111/17)
      - Interview of Lewis F. Powell, Jr., June 24, 1947 (Box-folder 111/18)
        Broadcast from Richmond, Virginia radio station WRVA.
      - Torch Club, October 7, 1947 (Box-folder 111/19)
        Re Charter of the City of Richmond, Virginia.
      - Statement By the Charter Commission, November 3, 1947 (Box-folder 111/20)
        Released for use by the Richmond News Leader.
      - Talk Over WRVA, November 3, 1947 (Box-folder 111/20)
        Radio address on behalf of Richmond Charter Commission.
      - Introduction of Colgate W. Darden, c. 1947 (Box-folder 111/21)
        Forum Club, Richmond, Virginia.
      - City Council Election in Richmond, Virginia, May 10, 1948 (Box-folder 111/22)
        Radio address on WLEE.
      - Re Sherwood Reeder, W. Stirling King, and John S. Davenport, III, c. 1948 (Box-folder 111/23)
        Re Richmond, Virginia city government.
      - Russian Espionage, April 14, 1949 (Box-folder 111/24)
        Omnibus Club, Richmond, Virginia.
      - Best Qualified for Governor, June, 13, 1949 (Box-folder 111/25)
        West End Businessmens' Association, Richmond, Virginia.
      - Horace Edwards For Governor, July 27, 1949 (Box-folder 111/26)
        For broadcast over WRVA, Richmond, Virginia.
      - Introduction of Sir Evelyn Wrench, November 16, 1949 (Box-folder 111/27)
        The English Speaking Union, Richmond, Virginia.
      - Good Citizenship, March 21, 1950 (Box-folder 111/28)
        Junior Chamber of Commerce, Richmond, Virginia.
      - Introduction of Henry R. Guild, October 17, 1950 (Box-folder 111/29)
        Community Chest, Richmond, Virginia.
      - Korean Crisis, November 16, 1950 (Box-folder 111/30)
        Faculty of Binford Junior High School, Richmond, Virginia.
      - Retiring as President of the Richmond Chamber of Commerce, January 11, 1951 (Box-folder 111/31)
      - Air Intelligence Function in Peace and War, January 22, 1952 (Box-folder 111/32)
        Talk to reserve unit, Richmond, Virginia.
      - Strategic Importance of the Arctic, February 26, 1952 (Box-folder 111/33)
      - Importance of Arctic to Defense of U.S.A., May 13, 1952 (Box-folder 111/33A)
        Goochland Rotary Club.
      - Eisenhower Is Stronger Than Taft, June 30, 1952 (Box-folder 111/34)
      - WRNL Radio Election Eve Address, November 3, 1952 (Box-folder 111/35)
      - Objectives of the Charter Commission, September 11, 1953 (Box-folder 111/36)
        Notes for speeches before civic clubs.
      - Union Theological Seminary, c. 1953 (Box-folder 111/37)
      - The Dixon-Yates Controversy, November 15, 1954 (Box-folder 111/38)
        Delivered at Forum Club, Richmond, Virginia. See also Dixon-Yates correspondence file in 2.1.2.
      - The James River Association, May 16, 1955 (Box-folder 111/39)
        Richmond, Virginia.
      - Interposition - A Twentieth Century Revival of Nullification, March 29, 1956 (Box-folder 111/40)
        Draft of article prepared for Va Law Review but was not submitted ...
      - St. Catherine's School Commencement, June 4, 1956 (Box-folder 111/41)
      - Capital Financing, April 29, 1957 (Box-folder 111/42)
        University of Virginia.
      - Contributory Negligence: A Necessary Check on the American Jury, June 26, 1957 (Box-folder 111/43)
        Joint Committee Session (ABA), Niblett Hall, London (England, July 26, 1957
      - The Place, September 7, 1957 (Box-folder 111/44)
        Draft of introductory material for ABA Journal presentation of speeches delivered at Westminster Hall
      - Military Position of U.S. vs. Russia, December 16, 1957 (Box-folder 111/45)
      - President Eisenhower's Proposed Education Plan, December 31, 1957 (Box-folder 111/46)
        Statement by Lewis F. Powell, Jr., Chairman, Richmond Public School Board.
      - Soviet Science, c. 1957 (Box-folder 111/47)
      - Soviet Education, c. 1957 (Box-folder 111/48)
      - President Eisenhower's Proposed Education Plan, January 2, 1958 (Box-folder 112/1)
      - Quality in Education: A National Necessity January 15, 1958 (Box-folder 112/2)
        Richmond Public School teachers. A printed version is also in this file.
      - Mary Mumford P.T.A., April 22, 1958 (Box-folder 112/3)
      - Richmond Rotary Club, April 29, 1958 (Box-folder 112/4)
      - Urgent Defense Requirements, June 26, 1958 (Box-folder 112/5)
        South Road Rotary
      - Trip To Soviet Union as a Member of Delegation Representing American Bar Association July-August 1958, August 1958 (Box-folder 112/6-11)